<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Kelimuttu.co</title>
  
  
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/"/>
  <updated>2020-09-20T14:24:32.299Z</updated>
  <id>http://kelimuttu.co/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Kelimutu</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The concept of &quot;home&quot;</title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/home/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/home/</id>
    <published>2020-09-20T12:49:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-09-20T14:24:32.299Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1472553384749-8596bacb90c5?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;q=80&amp;fm=jpg&amp;crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;dl=valentina-locatelli-P8bsrm8KbM0-unsplash.jpg" alt=""></p><p>I do think that if we are willing to follow the common pathways of life, which basically, have a faith in religion, do good at school, having good career, get married, kids, and blah blah blah, life is actually pretty easy. Like, it’s all there, and you just need to follow the pattern, right?</p><p>But, the thing with life is that, as we grow up, we started to question each concept one by one. Why do we have to believe in religion? Why do I have to be good at school? Maybe we just realize that working is actually sucks.. And ugh, maybe you think that there just too much pressure for kids and marriage.</p><p>For me, there’s one thing that I started to question the past few years since I work remotely. And that is the concept of a home. </p><p>When we talk about home, we think about a place where we spent most of our time. The key here, is the “a”. But what about, if we don’t feel enough with one place? It almost feels like you cheat on your home, right? Although, technically, home is not your spouse. Why do we have to choose one place we can call as home?</p><p>I used to be confused on how to reply when people ask me “where do you live now?”. Some people think that I’m still living in Bali, some thought that I moved out of the country. The thing is that, I can’t blame them to think that way since I was indeed move/travel a lot the past few years. Now that it’s not the case anymore, the urge to be in multiple places linger on me. Which btw, I’m just beginning to accept. </p><p>I’m just beginnig to accept that yes, I can’t stand the idea of having to decide on one place to live. At first, I feel like an outlier to say that I split my time between place A and place B. It almost feels like other people are being faithful to one spouse and here I am, decided to do polyandry, which doesn’t seem right. But, who decide right or not? </p><p>Then there’s a concept of domicile. But that merely means that you don’t live in a place where you came from anymore, which is not true in my case.</p><p>More and more, I feel like attaching our identity to a place is just a concept of the old days. Which is when our physical location matters a lot. But, in the era of the internet like today, I don’t feel like it matters a lot anymore. </p><p>I just finish reading <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/34051011-pachinko" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pachinko</a>, which is a novel about Korean living in Japan around the time of the world war II, and now it got me thinking about the concept of a country. Why do we have to attach our identity to our parent’s blood or their place of origin? Say a kid was born in America from an Indonesian parent. Does it make the kid an American or an Indonesian? And the ultimate question is, why does it matter?</p><p>I’m not talking about “citizen of the world”, or some kind of universal concept that believe that we’re all the same. Because, no, we’re not. We are raised in different culture and upbringing. I’m more concern about how we attach our identity to a man-made concept like a country and whether it’s still relevant or not in a globalized world like today. </p><p>I guess it’s still matters because the system is still exist. And I’m terrified to imagine that we’ll replicate this concept in another planet. I hope, whoever liberate the new planet and design the new ecosystem can come up with a better concept that doesn’t favor one group over the other. </p><p>Credit: <span>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@valentina_locatelli?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Valentina Locatelli</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Unsplash</a></span></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1472553384749-8596bacb90c5?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;q=80&amp;amp;fm=jpg&amp;amp;crop=entropy&amp;amp;cs=tinysrg
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Jar of thoughts" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/categories/Jar-of-thoughts/"/>
    
    
      <category term="English" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/tags/English/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>[music] Avril Lavigne - Nobody&#39;s Home</title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/nobody-s-home/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/nobody-s-home/</id>
    <published>2020-09-20T12:12:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-09-20T12:25:39.091Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="container"><br>  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Xwrd1DIqXjY" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen class="video"></iframe><br></div><p>So, I finally reunite with my  guitar after a few months we’ve been apart. I decided to cover this old song that I’ve been listenig to lately. </p><p>Listening to Avril, I feel like being thrown back in time when I was younger and care about very few things. Pandemic got me to retreat back to my childhood music so that’s why I’ve been listening to Avril again these days.</p><p>Anyway, it’s the very first time I show my face while doing music cover. You see, there’s a reason why I didn’t do that earlier, and that’s because it’s difficult for me to divide my focus from paying attention to the chords on the screen, all the while maintaining my guitar keys, trying to recall the lyric and staring at the camera. I’ve never been good at multi-tasking.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Xwrd1DIqXjY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypt
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Music" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/categories/Music/"/>
    
    
      <category term="English" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/tags/English/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>[Review] How to Do Nothing: Resisting the Attention Economy </title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/how-to-do-nothing/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/how-to-do-nothing/</id>
    <published>2020-08-20T10:33:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-08-23T00:01:28.805Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1565120319398-da008925fc1d?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;q=80&amp;fm=jpg&amp;crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;dl=jimmy-conover-BFzSwMG1nvs-unsplash.jpg&amp;w=1920" alt=""></p><blockquote><p>Among my students and in many of the people I know, I see so much energy, so much intensity, and so much anxiety. I see people caught up not just in notifications but in a mythology of productivity and progress, unable not only to rest but simply to see where they are.</p></blockquote><p>Sebagai seorang <em>“workaholic”</em>, judul buku ini menggelitik keingintahuan saya. Tadinya saya pikir buku ini akan menyuguhkan beberapa alasan mengapa kita tidak perlu ngoyo  dalam bekerja dan bagaimana menyeimbangkan kehidupan pribadi dan profesional (<em>work life balance</em>, istilah kerennya). Tidak disangka, buku ini jauh lebih dalam dari judulnya. Menurut saya, sub-judulnya -Resisting the Attention Economy- lebih cocok untuk menggambarkan isi buku ini. Meskipun begitu, saya akan setuju dengan pemilihan judul yang lebih ringan dengan harapan buku ini akan terdengar lebih menarik bagi lebih banyak orang.</p><blockquote><p>The happiest, most fulfilled moments of my life have been when I was completely aware of being alive, with all the hope, pain, and sorrow that that entails for any mortal being.</p></blockquote><p>Sebagai seorang seniman yang berasal dari keluarga yang erat dengan bidang teknologi, sang penulis, Jenny Odell, berhasil menyuguhkan materi yang <em>rebellious</em> dengan penyampaian yang sangat apik. Saya suka sekali bagaimana Odell menggunakan pendekatan seni dan filsafat untuk menggambarkan pemikirannya. Meskipun dari segi bahasa sebenarnya terasa agak berat bagi saya, namun untungnya, analogi yang disuguhkan masih bisa dimengerti dengan mudah.</p><p><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/42771901-how-to-do-nothing" target="_blank" rel="noopener">How to Do Nothing</a> intinya bercerita tentang pengaruh dari <em>attention economy</em> dan bagaimana kita bisa menyikapinya. Struktur pembahasannya sangat memudahkan kita untuk menyadari keterpautan antara <em>attention economy</em> dalam kehidupan sehari-hari dan bagaimana <em>instant refusal</em> mungkin bukan jalan terbaik untuk menyikapinya. Kita pun digiring untuk membuat strategi sendiri untuk menentukan apa yang akan kita lakukan dengan “perhatian” yang akhirnya berhasil kita peroleh kembali.</p><p>Saya merasa mendapat waktu yang sangat cocok saat membaca buku ini. Dengan PHK yang baru saja terjadi 2 minggu lalu di kantor saya, buku ini memberikan saya pandangan baru akan kapitalisme. Saya pun jadi berandai-andai, bagaimana jadinya, jika tidak pernah ada sistem kapitalis di bumi ini. Apakah manusia akan hidup dengan lebih selaras dengan alam? Apakah bumi ini jadi bisa ditinggali lebih lama lagi? Apakah pemanasan global akan tetap terjadi? Bagaimana sesungguhnya kita bisa hidup selaras dengan alam? Apa maksudnya?</p><p>Apalagi ditambah saya yang memang sedang berusaha mengurangi porsi waktu untuk bermain media sosial akhir-akhir ini. Penggunaan kata mengurangi di sini bahkan terkesan sederhana, karena faktanya, sejak tidak punya aplikasi media sosial lagi di ponsel, saya jadi merasa terbiasa dan cenderung menyukai ritme kehidupan saya yang sekarang tanpa akses cepat ke media sosial seperti biasanya. </p><p>Buku ini faktanya memang cocok untuk kalian yang memang skeptis akan <em>attention economy</em> dan sedang bergulat dengan pemikiran akan bagaimana seharusnya kita menyikapinya. Saya akan coba menjelaskan dengan membahas bagian per bagian dari buku ini: </p><h3 id="The-Case-for-Nothing"><a href="#The-Case-for-Nothing" class="headerlink" title="The Case for Nothing"></a>The Case for Nothing</h3><blockquote><p>In a situation where every waking moment has become the time in which we make our living, and when we submit even our leisure for numerical evaluation via likes on Facebook and Instagram, constantly checking on its performance like one checks a stock, monitoring the ongoing development of our personal brand, time becomes an economic resource that we can no longer justify spending on “nothing.” It provides no return on investment; it is simply too expensive.</p></blockquote><p>Di bagian pertama ini, Odell menjabarkan pentingnya tidak melakukan apapun untuk menstimulasi kita agar bisa mulai membuka diri dan peka akan hal-hal lain di luar hal-hal yang biasa kita perhatikan. </p><blockquote><p>Silence is not the absence of something but the presence of everything.</p></blockquote><p>Ketika kita dihadapkan dengan berbagai tekanan kehidupan (belajar, bekerja, mengurus keluarga, dll), media sosial memberikan kita <em>instant gratification</em> dengan tombol <em>likes, heart, retweet</em>, dan kemudahan untuk berkomunikasi yang bisa dilakukan dengan sangat cepat. Kita jadi bisa menghemat waktu yang kita bisa gunakan lagi untuk memperhatikan tanggung jawab kita yang lain. Hal tersebut semakin memperkuat gagasan bahwa mengkosongkan pikiran kita adalah kegiatan yang sangat mahal harganya. Padahal mengkosongkan pikiran di sini berperan penting untuk menetralkan gagasan dan mempertajam kepekaan kita akan keadaan sekitar. </p><h3 id="The-Impossibility-of-Retreat"><a href="#The-Impossibility-of-Retreat" class="headerlink" title="The Impossibility of Retreat"></a>The Impossibility of Retreat</h3><blockquote><p>… but their expression on social media so often feels like firecrackers setting off other firecrackers in a very small room that soon gets filled with smoke. Our aimless and desperate expressions on these platforms don’t do much for us, but they are hugely lucrative for advertisers and social media companies, since what drives the machine is not the content of information but the rate of engagement.</p></blockquote><p>Sangat mudah berargumentasi bahwa media sosial memang memiliki banyak manfaat meskipun memang punya akibat yang tidak bisa diabaikan begitu saja. Lalu tentu saja kita bisa berkesimpulan bahwa solusi dari itu semua adalah dengan menyeimbangkan kebaikan dan keburukannya.</p><blockquote><p>More generally, Epicurus observed that people in modern society ran in circles, unaware of the source of their unhappiness</p></blockquote><p>Tapi ketika kita menarik kembali ke akar eksistensi dari sistem itu sendiri, tidak bisa dipungkiri bahwa mata uang untuk berpartisipasi dalam sistem tersebut tidak lain adalah perhatian kita.</p><blockquote><p>Do you pack all your things in a van, say, “Fuck it,” and never look back? What responsibility do you have to the world you left behind, if any?</p></blockquote><p>Di bab ini Odell mulai menggiring kita untuk membayangkan jika ada banyak akibat buruk yang diakibatkan oleh <em>attention economy</em>, apakah menghindar adalah solusi? </p><p>Odell kemudian berargumentasi bahwa menarik diri tanpa mempertanyakan akar permasalahannya bukanlah pilihan yang paling bijaksana. Kita seharusnya justru harus berangkat dari pemahaman akan pengalaman kita masing-masing. </p><blockquote><p>To stand apart is to take the view of the outsider without leaving, always oriented toward what it is you would have left. It means not fleeing your enemy, but knowing your enemy</p></blockquote><p>Pada akhir bab ini Odell mulai memperkenalkan konsepnya untuk “stand apart” yang intinya adalah melakukan observasi akan interaksi yang kita lakukan selama ini. Dia mengumpamakannya sebagai memahami musuh yang kita hadapi. </p><h3 id="Anatomy-of-a-Refusal"><a href="#Anatomy-of-a-Refusal" class="headerlink" title="Anatomy of a Refusal"></a>Anatomy of a Refusal</h3><blockquote><p>If you can afford to pay a different kind of attention, you should.</p></blockquote><p>Bisa dibilang ini adalah bab yang paling saya sukai karena di bab ini penulis berusaha untuk realistis. Odell sadar, bahwa tidak semua orang mampu untuk menolak dan keluar dari sistem <em>attention economy</em>. </p><blockquote><p>It may be that refusal is only available as a tactic to people who already possess a great deal of social capital, people whose social standing will endure without Facebook and people whose livelihoods don’t require them to be constantly plugged in and reachable…These are people who have what [Kathleen] Noonan (2011) calls “the power to switch off.”</p></blockquote><p>Ia pun paham bahwa jalan untuk melawan <em>attention economy</em> tidaklah  mudah. Orang yang memilih pendekatan berbeda juga akan mendapat implikasi yang tidak awan dari masyawakat kebanyakan. Ia memberikan analogi dengan menceritakan beberapa artis dengan karya unik.</p><p>Salah satu artis yang ia sebutkan adalah <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pilvi_Takala" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pilvi Takala</a> yang merupakan seorang artis pertunjukan. Dalam salah satu karyanya, The Trainee, ia berpura-pura sebagai seorang karyawan magang di sebuah agensi teknologi. Namun kemudian ia hanya menghabiskan waktunya untuk menatap di depan meja kosong dan mondar-mandir di <em>elevator</em> dan mengaku sedang berusaha berpikir ketika rekannya bertanya. Pilvi ingin mengajak orang lain untuk mempertanyakan kembali gagasan bahwa tidak melakukan sesuatu adalah kegiatan yang sia-sia. </p><blockquote><p>“Appearing as if you’re doing nothing is seen as a threat to the general working order of the company, creating a sense of the unknown,” they wrote, adding solemnly, “The potential of nothing is everything.”</p></blockquote><p>Artis lain yang ia ceritakan, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tehching_Hsieh" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Techching Hsieh</a> juga menantang gagasan yang kurang lebih sama melalui karyanya, One Year Performance. Dalam Cage Piece, pertunjukan yang ia lakukan dalam rentang waktu satu tahun, ia mencoba mengurung diri dan tidak berbicara, menulis, membaca, atau mendengarkan TV/radio. Berkebalikan dengan pemikiran orang lain, Hsieh justru merasa bebas untuk berpikir meskipun ia dikurung secara fisik. </p><blockquote><p>“When a prisoner gets out of prison, they have to deal with society. It’s just a different cage. For me, I get joy from what I do … being in a cage I have ‘freedom thinking’, which is most important to me. Living as an illegal alien in New York, for example, I was not free because I was scared.” - <a href="https://pluralartmag.com/2019/11/03/tehching-hsieh-time-after-time/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pluralmag</a></p></blockquote><p>Penulis beranggapan bahwa kita perlu latihan untuk bisa berpaling dari <em>attention economy</em>. Ia pun mengakui bahwa dengan melakukan hal tersebut, kita akan mendapat respon skeptikal dari lingkungan, namun dengan melakukannya secara perlahan, kita jadi bisa mengevaluasi dan mengamati interaksi kita dengan lebih dalam. </p><blockquote><p>A real withdrawal of attention happens first and foremost in the mind. What is needed, then, is not a “once-and-for-all” type of quitting but ongoing training: the ability not just to withdraw attention, but to invest it somewhere else, to enlarge and proliferate it, to improve its acuity.</p></blockquote><h3 id="Exercises-in-Attention"><a href="#Exercises-in-Attention" class="headerlink" title="Exercises in Attention"></a>Exercises in Attention</h3><blockquote><p>We experience the externalities of the attention economy in little drips, so we tend to describe them with words of mild bemusement like “annoying” or “distracting.” But this is a grave misreading of their nature. In the short term, distractions can keep us from doing the things we want to do. In the longer term, however, they can accumulate and keep us from living the lives we want to live, or, even worse, undermine our capacities for reflection and self-regulation, making it harder, in the words of Harry Frankfurt, to “want what we want to want.” </p></blockquote><p>Di bagian ini Odell mengemukakan keterikatan antara perhatian dan kehendak. Ketika apa yang kita perhatikan mempengaruhi kemauan/kehendak pribadi kita, maka pengaruh <em>attention economy</em> di sini menjadi semakin signifikan. Di sinilah kebanyakan orang menjadi hilang kendali akan apa yang ia perhatikan ketika semua itu disuguhkan oleh media sosial.</p><blockquote><p>Instead of focusing on the problem of how to make persuasion more ethical, we should focus on empowering people to have more self control.</p></blockquote><p>Di sinilah kita perlu melatih diri untuk melakukan <em>redirect</em>/pengalihan arah dari hal-hal yang sebelumnya menyedot perhatian kita secara baku. </p><blockquote><p>“To [break a habit], Devine said, you have to be aware of it, motivated to change, and have a strategy for replacing it.”</p></blockquote><h3 id="Ecology-of-Strangers"><a href="#Ecology-of-Strangers" class="headerlink" title="Ecology of Strangers"></a>Ecology of Strangers</h3><blockquote><p>Bioregionalism teaches us of emergence, interdependence, and the impossibility of absolute boundaries. As physical beings, we are literally open to the world, suffused every second with air from somewhere else; as social beings, we are equally determined by our contexts. If we can embrace that, then we can begin to appreciate our and others’ identities as the emergent and fluid wonders that they are. Most of all, we can open ourselves to those new and previously unimaginable ideas that may arise from our combination, like the lightning that happens between an evanescent cloud and the ever-shifting ground.</p></blockquote><p>Di sinilah kecintaan penulis akan alam makin terpancar dengan lebih jelas. Di bab ini ia banyak membahas bioregionalism dan menganalogikan hal-hal baru yang sebelumnya tidak kita perhatikan sebagai hal/orang asing (<em>strangers</em>). </p><p>Sebagai manusia, sering kali kita merasa segan akan hal baru karena merasa asing. Padahal rasa asing tersebut muncul karena konsep pemisahan yang kita ciptakan sendiri. Negara, ras, bahasa, dan sebagainya, adalah konsep ciptaan manusia. </p><p>Padahal, alam sendiri bekerja dengan tidak mengenal batas. Air yang berasal dari satu negara mungkin akan tersapu dan menjadi hujan di negara lainnya. Suatu bahasa mungkin banyak menggunakan kata serapan dari bahasa lain. Hal tersebut membuktikan bahwa secara alami, di dunia ini tidak ada yang benar-benar asing karena semuanya telah saling terhubung antara satu dengan lainnya tanpa kita sadari. </p><blockquote><p>After all, if you were reading a book whose pages began to seem more and more similar until you were reading the same page over and over again, you would put the book down.</p></blockquote><p>Teknologi pun berperan untuk memperkuat segregasi tersebut. <a href="http://www.their.tube/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Their.tube</a> mencontohkan bagaimana kita akan disuguhi hal yang sama terus-menerus sehingga memperkuat <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confirmation_bias" target="_blank" rel="noopener">confirmation bias</a> sehingga lagi-lagi, kita jadi manusia yang takut akan hal asing dan hidup dalam gelembung kehidupan yang kita ciptakan sendiri. </p><h3 id="Restoring-the-Grounds-for-Thought"><a href="#Restoring-the-Grounds-for-Thought" class="headerlink" title="Restoring the Grounds for Thought"></a>Restoring the Grounds for Thought</h3><blockquote><p>IT’S TEMPTING TO conclude this book with a single recommendation about how to live. But I refuse to do that. That’s because the pitfalls of the attention economy can’t just be avoided by logging off and refusing the influence of persuasive design techniques; they also emerge at the intersection of issues of public space, environmental politics, class, and race.</p></blockquote><p>Pada akhirnya, semuanya kembali kepada pribadi masing-masing. Menolak <em>attention economy</em> jelas adalah hal yang memang direkomendasikan oleh buku ini, tapi kita juga diberi ruang untuk berpikir dan menentukan sendiri apa yang ingin kita lakukan dengan waktu dan atensi yang kita peroleh kembali.</p><blockquote><p>… doing nothing means disengaging from one framework (the attention economy) not only to give myself time to think, but to do something else in another framework.</p></blockquote><p>Photo Credit : <a href="https://unsplash.com/@jimmy_conover" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jimmy Conover</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Unsplash</a></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1565120319398-da008925fc1d?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;q=80&amp;amp;fm=jpg&amp;amp;crop=entropy&amp;amp;cs=tinysrg
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Review" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/categories/Review/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Bahasa Indonesia" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/tags/Bahasa-Indonesia/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Mengatur inbox Gmail dengan cara HEY</title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/hey/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/hey/</id>
    <published>2020-06-26T09:17:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-06-26T14:43:08.325Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/pasted-17.png" alt="upload successful"></p><p>Akhir-akhir ini, lini masa saya dipenuhi oleh orang-orang yang bercuit tentang <em>email service</em> baru yang sedang hits, <a href="https://hey.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hey</a>. Jujur, sebagai orang yang peduli dengan <em>email hygiene</em>, saya pun jadi lumayan tertarik untuk melihat apa sih bedanya Hey dengan <em>email service</em> biasa. </p><p>Akhirnya, saya menyempatkan diri untuk melihat <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UCeYTysLyGI" target="_blank" rel="noopener">video</a> perkenalan produk sepanjang 37 menit yang disampaikan oleh CEO Basecamp, Jason Fried. Kurang lebih, berikut inilah hal-hal yang ditawarkan oleh Hey: </p><ul><li><strong>The Screener</strong>: Ini ibaratnya seperti fitur <em>waiting room</em> di Zoom. Jadi, di sini kita bisa menyeleksi percakapan sebelum kita mengizinkan mereka untuk masuk ke imbox (bukan typo, mereka memang sengaja menyebut imbox sebagai representasi dari <em>important box</em>). Di sini kita juga bisa memblokir alamat <em>email</em> yang tidak kita inginkan. </li><li><strong>Unread emails</strong>: Hey memisahkan antara <em>email</em> yang sudah dan belum dibaca secara otomatis. Jadi kita nggak perlu <em>ngubek-ngubek</em> kotak masuk lagi untuk mencari <em>email </em>yang belum dibaca. </li><li><strong>Reply Later</strong>: Ini adalah semacam kategori yang mana memungkinkan kita mengumpulkan percakapan yang ingin kita balas di kemudian hari. </li><li><strong>Set Aside</strong>: Ini juga kategori lain untuk mengumpulkan percakapan yang mungkin tidak perlu kita balas, tapi isinya penting untuk kita ketahui. </li><li><strong>The Feed</strong>: Lagi-lagi ini semacam kategori untuk mengumpulkan percakapan yang tidak bersifat <em>time sensitive</em> seperti nawala/<em>newsletter</em>.</li><li><strong>Paper Trail</strong>: <em>Again</em>. Ini adalah kategori untuk memudahkan kita mengumpulkan jejak digital seperti tagihan, tanda terima/resi, dll. </li><li><strong>Rename email subject</strong></li><li><strong>Merge threads</strong></li><li><strong>Files center</strong></li><li><strong>Saved clips</strong></li><li><strong>Ignore thread</strong></li><li><strong>Spy tracker mark</strong></li><li><strong>Personal notes + sticky notes</strong></li></ul><p>Beberapa fitur sengaja tidak saya jabarkan karena tidak terlalu relevan dengan topik tulisan ini. Saran saya sih tonton <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UCeYTysLyGI" target="_blank" rel="noopener">videonya</a> saja kalau ingin tahu lebih lanjut. </p><p>Menariknya, dalam video tersebut Jason mengatakan bahwa <em>“You tell Hey where things go”</em>. Jadi ibaratnya, kita masih harus mengatur sendiri kemana surel-surel tersebut harus dikategorikan. Yang kemudian membuat saya berpikir “ya itu mah sama aja kaya <em>email service</em> yang lain.” Meskipun tentu, dengan Hey kita memang dimudahkan untuk melakukannya. Selain itu, bagi saya Hey juga masih memiliki daya tarik tersendiri dari fitur-fitur tambahan lain yang memang tidak ada di <em>email service</em> pada umumnya. </p><p>Nah bagi kalian yang mungkin tertarik dengan fitur pengkategorian dari Hey tapi belum mau membayar 99 USD per tahun, saya punya trik yang kurang lebih memiliki fungsi yang sama. Trik ini pun sudah saya terapkan di <em>email</em> kantor dari sekitar setahun yang lalu dan sejauh ini membantu saya mengatur <em>inbox</em> jadi lebih rapi.</p><p><img src="/images/pasted-10.png" alt="upload successful"></p><p>Perlu dicatat bahwa trik ini saya pelajari pertama kali dari <a href="https://klinger.io/post/71640845938/dont-drown-in-email-how-to-use-gmail-more" target="_blank" rel="noopener">blognya Andreas Klinger</a> yang ia tulis dari tahun 2013 jadi beberapa pengaturan memang sudah agak berbeda dibandingkan sekarang. Salah satu rekan saya yang saya beri tahu trik ini pun sempat <a href="https://bacharakis.com/2020/04/08/zero-inbox/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">menulis</a> tentang hal yang kurang lebih sama. </p><p>Kali ini, saya mencoba mereplikasi trik tersebut dengan gaya  pengkategorian pada Hey pada akun surel/<em>email</em> pribadi saya yang menggunakan <em>email service</em> sejuta umat, Gmail. Jika kalian menggunakan Gmail dengan pengaturan baku/<em>default</em>, tampilan <em>inbox</em> kalian mungkin akan terlihat seperti ini: </p><p><img src="/images/pasted-11.png" alt="upload successful"></p><p>Berikut langkah-langkah yang perlu diikuti untuk mengatur akun Gmail kalian dengan cara Hey: </p><h2 id="Mengatur-multiple-inboxes"><a href="#Mengatur-multiple-inboxes" class="headerlink" title="Mengatur multiple inboxes:"></a>Mengatur multiple inboxes:</h2><p>Langkah pertama: </p><ul><li>Klik ikon Settings yang ada di pojok kanan atas dari laman inbox kalian.</li><li>Sebuah panel akan muncul di sebelah kanan halaman. Pada bagian Inbox Type, pilih Multiple inboxes, lalu klik Customize.<br><img src="/images/pasted-12.png" alt="upload successful"></li><li>Kalian akan diarahkan ke Settings &gt; Inbox. Pada bagian Multiple Inbox Sections, atur kategori kalian menjadi seperti berikut: <ul><li>has:red-bang -&gt; Reply Later</li><li>has:yellow-bang -&gt;  Set Aside</li><li>label:The-Feed -&gt; The Feed</li><li>label:Paper-Trail -&gt; Paper Trail</li></ul></li><li>Pada bagian Multiple inbox position, pilih Right of the inbox. </li><li>Klik Save Changes ketika selesai.</li></ul><p>Langkah kedua: </p><ul><li>Dari menu Settings tadi, pilih tab General.<br><img src="/images/pasted-13.png" alt="upload successful"></li><li>Pagi bagian Stars, seret ikon yang ingin kalian pakai (dalam hal ini saya menggunakan tanda seru yang merah dan kuning) ke bagian In Use, lalu klik Save Changes. </li></ul><p>Sebenarnya, kalian bisa memilih ikon apa saja yang ingin kalian pakai. Hanya saja, pastikan sesuai dengan apa yang kalian atur sebelumnya di bagian Multiple Inboxes. </p><p>Jika berhasil, <em>inbox</em> kalian akan jadi seperti ini.</p><p><img src="/images/pasted-14.png" alt="upload successful"></p><p>Setelah berhasil membuat kategori, sekarang kita bisa mulai mengatur <em>filtering</em> sehingga di masa depan semuanya bisa terotomatisasi. Tolong dicatat, bahwa ini mungkin akan memakan banyak waktu, terutama jika kalian berlangganan banyak layanan/<em>services</em> maupun nawala/<em>newsletter</em>.</p><h2 id="Mengatur-filtering"><a href="#Mengatur-filtering" class="headerlink" title="Mengatur filtering:"></a>Mengatur <em>filtering</em>:</h2><p><img src="/images/pasted-15.png" alt="upload successful"></p><p>Mengatur percakapan yang akan dimasukan ke The Feed/Paper Trail: </p><ul><li>Klik tanda centang pada tiap percakapan yang ingin kalian masukan ke kategori The Feed. </li><li>Klik tanda titik tiga -&gt; Filter messages like these -&gt; Create filter</li><li>Klik centang pada Skip the Inbox (Archieve it), Apply the label (buat label “The Feed”) dan pilih label tersebut, terakhir centang bagian Also apply filter to matching conversations juga lalu klik Create Filter. </li><li>Lakukan hal yang sama untuk mengatur filtering untuk kategori Paper Trail</li></ul><p>Saran saya, pilih percakapan yang memang penting atau nawala yang biasa kalian ikuti saja, lalu lainnya bisa dicicil sambil jalan. </p><p>Untuk memasukan percakapan ke kategori Reply Later atau Set Aside, kalian hanya perlu mengetuk ikon bintang sampai ikonnya sesuai dengan yang kalian atur tadi. </p><p>Berikutnya sekaligus langkah terakhir adalah membersihkan <em>inbox</em>. </p><p><img src="/images/pasted-16.png" alt="upload successful"></p><h2 id="Mencapai-inbox-zero"><a href="#Mencapai-inbox-zero" class="headerlink" title="Mencapai inbox zero:"></a>Mencapai <em>inbox zero</em>:</h2><ul><li>Centang semua percakapan.</li><li>Pilih Archieve.</li><li>Klik OK pada kotak konfirmasi bulk action.</li><li>Lakukan hal yang sama pada kategori/label percakapan yang lain. </li></ul><p><img src="/images/pasted-9.png" alt="upload successful"></p><p>Hasilnya, <em>inbox</em> kalian akan bersih dan tertata rapi. Jika menggunakan analogi Hey, <em>inbox</em> di sebelah kiri akan berfungsi sebagai area The Screener dan menampung surel/<em>email</em> yang belum dibaca. Sedangkan di sebelah kanan menampung kategori Reply Later, Set Aside, The Feed, dan Paper Trail.</p><p>Selamat mencoba!</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pasted-17.png&quot; alt=&quot;upload successful&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Akhir-akhir ini, lini masa saya dipenuhi oleh orang-orang yang bercuit t
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Tips and Trick" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/categories/Tips-and-Trick/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Bahasa Indonesia" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/tags/Bahasa-Indonesia/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>This too shall pass</title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/this-too-shall-pass/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/this-too-shall-pass/</id>
    <published>2020-06-20T16:26:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-06-21T14:08:47.486Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1526112455121-272736767b9e?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;q=80&amp;fm=jpg&amp;crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;dl=jeremy-stenuit-3mErKfgolzM-unsplash.jpg" alt=""></p><p>My experience with Covid-19 stretched back from the end of January, when I visited Berlin for a company meeting. I remember I had a conversation with a colleague who were coming from China to get to know how was the situation there. At that time, I thought, Corona is only exist in China. I even made <a href="https://twitter.com/kelimuttu/status/1228238491995136000" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a joke</a> about it on Twitter. Gee, that was very stupid of me.</p><p>And then life goes on and I have to go on another business trip. This time is to Toronto in the end of February. It was the time when mask and hand sanitizer were luxurious items. And I couldn’t help but to be panicked this time. The fact that I would have a layover in Hong Kong terrify me even more. It was just natural that I even think about to cancel the trip. But then I proceed.</p><p>I was extremely careful on that trip, though. The fact that the plane to Hong Kong was half-empty (even half is a generous word of choice) feels more like a sign that this shit was real. When I arrived at Hong Kong and saw that the airport was also almost empty, it terrifies me even more. I even avoid eating anything during the layover in Hong Kong, eventhough I was starving at that time. I stayed close to the toilet in the gate and washed my hands more than ever.</p><p>But then coming home from that trip alive and healthy, I feel that I just passed a test. Which is a completely stupid feeling now that I think about it. I remember I even think about to attend a concert in Singapore on the first week of March. Thank goodness the concert was postponed. That would be so dumb if I really come.</p><p>But that was not the pinnacle of Covid-19 stress that I’ve experienced. By mid-March, when I was in Jakarta, I received a news that my nephew who stay in my hometown was hospitalized for blood infection. I was frustrated by the fact that I couldn’t visit him. Around the same time, I heard from a friend of mine who was also hospitalized because he was suspected of Covid-19. At this point, I was sickened by the pandemic. But, rather than fear, what I feel at that time was more like anger.</p><p>I detest the virus. But with time, I realized that it’s probably not the wisest reaction to this situation. We’re not going to stop the pandemic by hating the virus. The virus itself is neutral. It’s probably doesn’t even realize what harm it causes us.</p><p>My fear from that trip to Toronto has proven to be effective for me (please, underline the “for me” part). Although, the problem with that was that I feel too much pressure. And that exactly what turn me into a “takabur” person (now it’s your turn to Google it down, English speaking reader), which it shouldn’t have to. When the fear is too high, we expect too much satisfaction from the payoff. </p><p>The fact is, we just need a little bit of fear to prevent us from doing stupid things. In this situation, fear is much needed to remind us to be cautious. Sure, it wouldn’t guarantee 100% that it could prevent us from getting the virus. But at least, when we have fear, it means that we acknowledge that we have a fair amount of share to do something that wouldn’t cause more trouble.</p><p>Now after a few months have passed, I thought that I’ve got a grip of the situation. I think that I’ve maintained a healthy dose of fear, just enough to remind me to be cautious. I even had fun during <a href="/isolation">isolation</a>. However, something else happened to me lately. I started dreaming about travelling and having party which is insane because I’m not even a party person.</p><p>I know exactly the moment I dream about something, that thing is seriously getting into my mind. So yeah, just when I feel like I get used to the situation, the fear in me is changing its shape. </p><p>I don’t know, though. Maybe I’m just too invested on work lately that I forget to take care of my own sanity. I know I don’t deserve to complain about the situation. I just think that I’m not the only person to feel this and I hope I could lessen my burden by sharing it. </p><p>I do think that acknowledging our fear is a way to accept and make peace with it. This pandemic is a collective concern which means that our burden might be felt by a lot of other people out there.</p><p>For now, I’m just trying believe that this too shall pass someday.</p><p>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@stenuitj?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jérémy Stenuit</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Unsplash</a></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1526112455121-272736767b9e?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;q=80&amp;amp;fm=jpg&amp;amp;crop=entropy&amp;amp;cs=tinysrg
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Jar of thoughts" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/categories/Jar-of-thoughts/"/>
    
    
      <category term="English" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/tags/English/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>[Review] Cancel the Wedding</title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/cancel-the-wedding/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/cancel-the-wedding/</id>
    <published>2020-05-06T14:12:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-05-07T14:13:30.127Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1468818438311-4bab781ab9b8?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;q=80&amp;fm=jpg&amp;crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;dl=averie-woodard-5d20kdvFCfA-unsplash.jpg&amp;w=1920" alt=""></p><p>Jarang-jarang nih, saya membuat review novel. Tapi saking serunya novel yang satu ini (plus, mumpung saya lagi gabut), boleh lah ya. </p><blockquote><p>Leo and I were vanilla ice cream. Consistent but bland.</p></blockquote><p>Seperti judulnya yang <em>straight forward</em>, <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18698835-cancel-the-wedding" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cancel The Wedding</a> ini menceritakan tentang kehidupan Olivia yang sedang mengalami kebimbangan. Meskipun punya kehidupan berkecukupan dan sudah bertunangan dengan pasangan yang bisa dibilang <em>decent</em>, ia masih belum yakin ketika Leo (tunangannya) mengajaknya menikah. Karena itu, ia memutuskan melakukan road trip bersama ponakannya (Logan) ke Huntley, Georgia, untuk mengenal tempat kelahiran ibunya yang sudah meninggal setahun lalu. Sebelum meninggal, ibunya memang berpesan supaya keduanya anaknya menabur abunya di tanah kelahirannya. Namun sampai sekarang, Olivia dan Georgia (kakak Olivia) belum sempat juga memenuhi permintaan ibunya. </p><blockquote><p>Why are relationships between mothers and daughters always so complicated?</p></blockquote><p>Saya sendiri sebenarnya mengira jika novel ini akan berfokus pada hubungan ibu dan anak. Itu juga yang awalnya membuat saya tertarik pada novel ini. Namun ternyata, ceritanya lebih seperti kombinasi antara drama, percintaan, dan misteri. </p><blockquote><p>All of my instincts recoiled. How weak a person do you have to be to need another person in order to breathe? “I don’t need someone to rescue me like that, Mom.”</p></blockquote><p>Mungkinkah Olivia sedang mengalami quarter life crisis di usia 32 tahun? Entahlah.. Yang jelas, permintaan ibunya yang belum sempat ia penuhi menjadi alasan yang empuk baginya untuk menghindar sementara dari Leo dan Georgia untuk berpikir dan merenungkan kehidupannya. </p><blockquote><p>When someone did or said something particularly stupid, instead of arguing back my mom would shake her head very slowly and say, “Bless her heart.” As if it wasn’t worth getting upset over, clearly God had made that person stupid and all you could do for the ignorant was feel pity and pray for a jump in their IQ.</p></blockquote><p>Tapi ternyata, perjalanan yang rencananya hanya beberapa hari malah jadi berlangsung lebih lama setelah ia menemukan rahasia masa lalu ibunya yang ia tak pernah ketahui. Menguak satu per satu rahasia tersebut membuatnya menyadari jika ibunya memiliki sisi  lain yang belum pernah ia kenal sebelumnya. Ia pun jadi penasaran untuk mencari tahu lebih lanjut terutama kenapa ibunya menutupi masa lalunya selama ini. </p><blockquote><p>It’s amazing how completely still the body can be when the mind is racing.</p></blockquote><p>Sulit untuk percaya jika ini adalah karya pertama <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/7355315.Carolyn_T_Dingman" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Carolyn T. Dingman</a> karena ceritanya begitu memikat dan membuat pembacanya susah berhenti. Plot cerita dan karakter di buku ini bisa dibilang cukup matang. Dan meski tidak ada karakter penulisannya yang menonjol, tapi teknik penulisan Carolyn di buku ini menurut saya sangat pas untuk membuat pembaca cukup penasaran untuk mengikuti ceritanya. </p><blockquote><p>Being with someone shouldn’t be so much work.</p></blockquote><p>Apalagi kisah manis antara Olivia dengan Elliott (pria yang membantunya menyelidiki masa lalu ibunya) jadi daya tarik tersendiri dari keseluruhan cerita di buku ini. Karakter Elliott yang sungguh <em>lovable</em> membuat pembaca ikut jatuh hati dengan mudah. Banyak sekali momen mereka yang membuat saya jadi ikut tersenyum ketika membacanya. Gemes, kalau bahasa anak sekarang. </p><blockquote><p>And I think I had finally come to understand what she meant about needing someone in order to breathe.</p></blockquote><p>Bisa dibilang, ceritanya berakhir dengan <em>satisfying</em>. Dan overall, saya rasa buku ini cocok untuk dinikmati di akhir pekan ketika kalian punya banyak waktu sehingga kalian tidak dibuat penasaran. Atau bisa juga sih, dicicil sembari nunggu buka puasa (hashtag #ngabuburead). Kalau bukan penyuka novel seperti saya aja suka, mungkin kalian perlu coba juga. </p><p>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@averieclaire?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText" target="_blank" rel="noopener">averie woodard</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Unsplash</a></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1468818438311-4bab781ab9b8?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;q=80&amp;amp;fm=jpg&amp;amp;crop=entropy&amp;amp;cs=tinysrg
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Review" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/categories/Review/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Bahasa Indonesia" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/tags/Bahasa-Indonesia/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Thoughts during isolation</title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/isolation/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/isolation/</id>
    <published>2020-05-02T13:02:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-05-02T16:01:08.606Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been almost 10 days since I isolate myself 15 kilometers away from where my family live. At first, I thought, what am I gonna do? But actually, at this point, I started to like this experience. Especially at 6 pm, during iftar, when I got to eat without watching local television channel. Instead, I put on Korean drama or stand up comedies, depending on my mood, which you can’t really do when you live with your family.</p><p>I also come to like that I don’t have to worry about offending other people for not talking the whole day. It’s a given, especially when you fast. You don’t really want to talk when the last time you drink water was 8 hours ago.</p><p>I have a new hobby, though. Which is to type using speech to text feature on my phone (which is how I create the initial draft for this post). You might think that I do that because I missed talking to people (not that this is entirely wrong), but I actually do that <del>because I’m lazy</del> to reduce my screen time. I picked it up after I got CVS or digital eye strain, which basically is a sign that I need to have other activities than staring at the screen. The other day, I was saying “page break” but my phone recognize it as “biiiiitch break”. It’s amazing to see how technology is so advance these days. </p><p>When I got the CVS, though, I felt like a kid whose toys were taken. I looooove working and it was my main activity that could distract me from my solitude during the isolation. I remember I talked to my housemate when I was still in Jakarta that I’m excited about monday because I finally got to do something. Now that I have to rest my eyes, I switch to my other hobbies, which is to sleep. Which is not going really well so far because it makes my body ache and stiff now that I got too much of it.</p><p>And probably just like million other people, I cook more ever since I got to stay at home more (if not all the time). If you think about it, cook for yourself is like an exercise of self-acceptance. No matter how bad they are, you’re likely going to finish them anyway. Because heeey! You should take a pride on what you’ve made. Think about it like putting your drawing in a frame. Besides, living by yourselves means that you don’t have many choices.</p><p>I’ve also been keeping a food diary these days. I have a folder on my phone where I put pictures of the food that I eat. I especially took a lot of photos of my cooking. Not that I’m proud of it, but just in case I got food poisoning, I would have a neat documentation of what I had. </p><p>I honestly like my cooking, though. I feel like I have this hidden talent in me that I just discover recently. I would just randomly throw a few stuff that I have in the fridge and turn it into a dish. I don’t even look up at a recipe, I would just cook them randomly and eat them like it’s the best food in the world. Because to be fair, it is, at least the best that I could have at the moment.</p><p>Also, these days, I’ve been cleaning a lot like a freak. I  would spill a bit of oil on the stove and I would clean the whole kitchen. The other day, I cleaned my bathroom until the toilet turned like a brand new just like what you see in a commercial. It’s fascinating to see how you develop a lot of skills even during a difficult time like this. </p><p>But in all seriousness, I think the best learning that I come to learn these days is to accept that we don’t have much control over our lives. I would probably believe if you tell me that our health minister has resigned from his position because I give up following the news. There’s too much sorrow when I look at the timeline so I stay away from it (I do aware of what people have done with chocolate sprinkle, though). I guess this is just an attempt to make peace with myself. Until I’m ready to take on the harsh world, I think I will make do with this solitude.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;It’s been almost 10 days since I isolate myself 15 kilometers away from where my family live. At first, I thought, what am I gonna do? Bu
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Jar of thoughts" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/categories/Jar-of-thoughts/"/>
    
    
      <category term="English" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/tags/English/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Bare minimum</title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/bare-minimum/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/bare-minimum/</id>
    <published>2020-04-04T11:12:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-04-04T13:33:13.466Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/49733983388/in/dateposted-public/" title="2020-04-04_08-10-54" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49733983388_acf8ac5c36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="2020-04-04_08-10-54"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p><p>When I was a kid, me and friends used to exchange personal bio with each other. We will use a fancy loose-leaf binder paper and write things that define our identity like our hobby, favorite food, favorite band, etc. That’s pretty much how we learn to get to know each other.</p><p>As we grow older, we use things like our major in college, our job, or our expertise to give other people ideas of who we really are. It’s almost like, we need to have a certain label to exist in this world. And I used to hate that. </p><p>I have this idea in my mind that I want people to know me just as a human being. Or even a lump of raw meat. Scrapping those identities like personality, religion, job, activity, or hobby. Think about a variable in programming language that doesn’t have any value.</p><p><code> int i; </code></p><p>Very basic and simple. No attachment of any kind.</p><p>But then this pandemic is kind of reminded me of something important. It’s heartbreaking to see people lose their family members, job, or simply not be able to do their routines. And those things, however mundane, are things that make up our lives as a human. </p><blockquote><p><strong>I guess the hardest part of all this is to realize how empty our lives are without those nitty-gritty details.</strong></p></blockquote><p>Sure, you can have a variable without any value. But those values are basically what makes us unique. If it weren’t for those values, then we’ll be nothing. Just like it doesn’t make sense to allocate memory for a variable that has no value. </p><p>I guess I’ve been wrong all this time. The most important part of our life is not the variable, but those values. Just like how variables are merely a name you give to computer memory locations which are used to store values in a computer program, we are merely containers for those nitty-gritty details of our lives. If we scrap out those details, then we become an empty container. </p><p>And in time like this, when our capacity and movement is very limited, it makes us rethink about which values are more important for us. Priority over urgency. Significance on top of responsibility. Necessity over totality.</p><p>I hope you can also use this moment to contemplate. How would you like to fill your container back when things restored to normal. (:</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/49733983388/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;2020-04-04_08-10-
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Jar of thoughts" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/categories/Jar-of-thoughts/"/>
    
    
      <category term="English" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/tags/English/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>2020</title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/2020/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/2020/</id>
    <published>2020-01-02T13:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-01-05T07:04:18.528Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/pasted-3.png" alt="upload successful"></p><p>Hello folks!</p><p>Anyway, how’s your decade doing? I hope you don’t feel pressured after reading those decade’s recap from some random people on the internet. You do you, ok?</p><p>And don’t worry about it. I’m not going to recap what has been a decade for me (it’s probably boring). I was just going to do what I’ve been doing for the past 2 years, which is to review the previous year and update my value for the next one.</p><p>So, 2019. Alright. 2019 for me has been a year that reminded me to be grateful. There are lots of things whether it’s related to family, career, or personal goal that got me thinking if I was very lucky last year.</p><p>Although of course, that doesn’t mean that I don’t work hard to get them. Work hard and focus on the goal are definitely part of the equation. It’s just hard to believe that so many good things happened in the same year. God must’ve been very kind to me, and I can’t help but feel that <a href="/too-much-happiness/">I’m just super blessed</a>. Alhamdulillah.. (: </p><p>Alright. Time for a few highlights from 2019: </p><ul><li><strong>My first nephew was born</strong><br>And he’s probably the best thing that ever happened to me in 2019. Like, how can I ask for a better thing to start a new year than to have a newborn nephew? I’m very grateful that I spent the majority of my time this year in my hometown so that I could watch him grow up closely. My year (and my entire family’s) definitely wouldn’t be the same without him. </li><li><strong>Add-ons outage</strong><br>If you’re a Firefox user, you probably remember about the add-ons certificate issue that breaks all Firefox’s add-ons in May (<a href="https://hacks.mozilla.org/2019/05/technical-details-on-the-recent-firefox-add-on-outage/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here</a>‘s a technical explanation from Mozilla CTO). During the issue and as an interim support community manager at that time, I was very proud of how our community worked hand in hand during the crisis and help a lot of (and I mean, LOTS OF) users in multiple languages. There’s even <a href="https://associationsnow.com/2019/05/an-adept-lesson-in-crisis-communications-on-social-media/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an online media</a> that cover how we handle the incident. Kudos to all Mozillians who worked over the weekend during the incident (there are countless, I can’t even 😭). Witnessing their spirit and working along with them is what keeps me excited to work. </li><li><strong>In the spirit of sharing</strong><br>I’m probably an introvert, but if you know me better, you might know that I love to share. And I guess, 2019 taught me that in order to share, it’s not necessary that I have to be in the spotlight. Instead, we could do it by facilitating the sharing and help others to share what they’ve learned. In early March, I was very proud that I managed to organize Global Diversity CFP Day Jakarta along with a friend, <a href="https://galuh.me/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Galuh</a>. The collaboration then evolved and goes beyond that. In April, we decided to start a podcast called <a href="kartiniteknologi.id/">Kartini Teknologi</a> to empower more women to join the tech scene. We talked to 10 amazing Indonesian women this year in our podcast, which I definitely learn a lot from. I even managed to meet with my role model during university, kak <a href="twitter.com/alandakariza">Alanda Kariza</a> and her son, Sena. And then in October, in collaboration with the <a href="forum.kerjaremote.co.id/">remote worker community</a>, we managed to organize the first Hacktoberfest in Bali. That was my first event ever in Bali and I hope we would be able to collaborate more in the future!</li><li><strong>Now I understand what they’ve been saying about Jogja</strong><br>I wouldn’t say that I travel a lot in 2019  although I visited Whistler at the beginning of the year, and then Berlin and Jogja for a couple of times, as well as Gresik and Bali in September and October. Whistler Blackcomb was really beautiful (I mean, riding gondolo while spotting bear was just amazing). And now after 3 visits, I keep on loving Berlin more and more. A friend perfectly captured my feeling by saying that Berlin is just like beer. You wouldn’t like it the first time you try it, but then it grows on you. It’s just so true. Another city that gets me addicted to this year is Jogja. Now I no longer <a href="/jogja/">wonder</a> why people like it so much. </li><li><strong>I can finally die in peace, now that I published my book</strong><br>I was half-joking with a friend when I said that I would be a haunting spirit if I die before I publish my book. Except that it’s not really a joke. Publish a book has been a long outstanding dream that I really wish to accomplish and I’m very grateful that I managed to make it come true in 2019. It has been a challenging process which leads me to understand the publishing world a little bit better. I can’t thank you enough for everyone involved in the process of scoping, writing, editing, as well as for the early readers who helped me to improve the initial script. I try to be really honest in the book and shared a lot of insecurities that I felt during my quarter-life crisis phase to the point that it made me scared whenever I hear people read it. But it’s all worth it. Some book ideas are dancing in my mind but I guess I need to keep my promise and finish that one book about remote working first. Apart from publishing my book, I feel also grateful to be able to attend 3 literary festivals this year. One is the Ubud Writer and Reader Festival, in which I came as a volunteer. And the other two which I came as an attendee are Indonesia Writers Festival in UMN and Patjar Merah in Semarang.</li><li><strong>All these things are tied to a year of journaling</strong><br>I made a promise to myself to write journal more regularly in  2019, which I did. It’s probably the most successful resolution from last year which I’ll definitely recommend to everyone. Journaling has helped me to clear my mind and force me to think about what I really feel. To keep it simple, I created a structure for the journal that consists of 3 questions: <ul><li>What I accomplish today: Although I love lying down (aka <em>rebahan</em>), at the end of the day, I would be disappointed if I got nothing done during the day. This question keeps me accountable to do at least something meaningful that I can put here at the end of the day. </li><li>What made me happy: What we’ve done is not necessarily what makes us happy, right? I put this question as a reminder of what are the things that really meaningful to me.</li><li>What I can do better: I could just put “What went wrong” here. But, instead of focusing on the bad side, I want to challenge myself to think about what I can do to make it better. </li></ul></li></ul><p>Alright, I had enough of reminiscing 2019. Now, to start  2020 with a strong footing, let’s update a set of values that I would like to hold on to in the next 12 months (caution: these are my personal goals. Take it only as a reference if you would like to create your own): </p><ol><li><strong>Health</strong><br>Force yourself to eat even if you don’t feel like eating. Cook, if it makes you excited to eat. Exercise, not only when your body is aching, but do it as a prevention. </li><li><strong>Bravery</strong><br>Insecurities and bravery can sit together and you just need to manage them simultaneously. Trust me! </li><li><strong>Minimalism</strong><br>Don’t fall into that compulsive habit anymore, Kiki. This will keep you to focus on what’s really important. </li><li><strong>Creativity</strong><br>Think about balancing consumption and creation. You need that in order to be a better creator. </li><li><strong>On people</strong><br>You do understand that you don’t have to keep everyone happy, right? </li><li><strong>Give back</strong><br>Be better on this. Period.</li><li><strong>On state of mind</strong><br>Thanks for holding on when things get hard but free your mind by being more open to others. Trust me, it’s worth it! </li><li><strong>On relaxing</strong><br>Get more sleep, spend your annual leave, and don’t feel guilty for going places without having another reason but to have fun!</li></ol><p>What about you? How many carry-on resolutions you have this year? </p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pasted-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;upload successful&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello folks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, how’s your decade doing? I hope you don’t fee
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="New Year Resolutions" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/categories/New-Year-Resolutions/"/>
    
    
      <category term="English" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/tags/English/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>[music] Daniel Caesar ft. H.E.R. - Best Part</title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/best-part/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/best-part/</id>
    <published>2019-12-29T13:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-12-29T13:41:55.641Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="container"><br>  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qTdeDJqV8Uw" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen class="video"></iframe><br></div><p>It’s been awhile since I play with my guitalele. You can see here that I’m not really good with Bm and Gm yet. But heck, that’s what we call a learning process, right? (wink)</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qTdeDJqV8Uw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypt
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Music" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/categories/Music/"/>
    
    
      <category term="English" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/tags/English/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>What Jakarta could offer? &quot;Options&quot;</title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/story-about-options/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/story-about-options/</id>
    <published>2019-12-13T05:28:08.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-12-13T06:42:15.484Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/49211429048/in/album-72157709043860993/" title="2019-12-13_01-26-09" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49211429048_b91d9d6688_b.jpg" width="1024" height="472" alt="2019-12-13_01-26-09"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p><p>I’ve been thinking a lot about what makes me decided to go back to Jakarta. And I guess I found the answer, which seems obvious from the title of this post. Options.</p><p>“Options” is a luxury. We can’t afford “options” if we have less capital. So the idea of being presented with various “options” make us somehow feel like we have a lot. And of course, as a human, we like that feeling. It’s just very natural for us to feel satisfied with abundance.</p><p>But the problem with “options” is the illusion that “we have it all” while it’s not the case in most cases. Because “options” is only an entrance. “Options” is an alley on most supermarkets that has lots of products. You have to examine the products to make sure which one you’d like to have and go to the cashier to make a final decision.</p><p>Personally, I prefer to feel that I don’t have many options since it tends lead me to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decision_fatigue" target="_blank" rel="noopener">decision fatigue</a> (sidenote: <a href="https://www.developgoodhabits.com/decision-fatigue/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here</a>‘s a helpful article to overcome decision fatigue). And as a remote worker who has a lot of freedom (read: “options”), let me tell you that you need certain dicipline (read: “decision making”) to make it work. </p><p>Let’s just say that it’s an irony that I sign up for this decision for having more options. Because in the end, I would agree that having “options” is still necessary. “Options” make benchmarking possible. Options put our brains to work. Having options is what differentiates us from our childhood. </p><p>I think in the end, let’s just agree that options is not the goal. We haven’t even start if we’re still thinking about which option that could offer us with the most benefit. Let’s remember that the hard work relies on the analytical thinking on the decision making process. We should strive for a decision, not for more options. (;</p><p>PS: </p><p>Read my <a href="/jakarta/">other post</a> about Jakarta</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/49211429048/in/album-72157709043860993/&quot; title=&quot;2019-12-13_
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Talking about my new book..</title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/khsa/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/khsa/</id>
    <published>2019-10-12T04:07:33.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-10-13T17:45:01.144Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/pasted-2.png" alt="upload successful"></p><p>Writing has always been part of me. I always enjoy the whole process of channeling my thoughts and pour it into chains of words. It’s liberating, as if I just released the agonizing part of my body by letting the words out. But in contrary, at the same time it also gave me more clarity on what I actually feel about lots of things. It helps me to shade some doubts so that I finally see what I actually feel and how to react to that feeling. It’s been a private activity so far, except for a few stuff that I shared on my blog.</p><p>However, maybe just like a normal person, I also knew that I would like to showcase it publicly someday. I knew I always wanted to publish a book. Little did I know that I could finally realize that dream just recently. </p><p>It felt surreal and I still can’t believe that I could managed to find the courage to put my words out there. Especially since it’s my own story. Some part of me said that I would just embarrass myself by doing this. However, I thought that it’s just fear doing its job and I should be doing mine as well which is, to overcome it. </p><p>I’ve been fascinated my memoir for the past couple of years and I knew that I always want to write one. But my life is probably too boring to be shared so I decided to embark a new adventure for a whole year in 2018 by moving to Bali and do some experiments with my life. </p><p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/48877648537/in/album-72157711281897473/" title="IMG_20171119_124233-01" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48877648537_f9407cd222_k.jpg" width="1536" height="2048" alt="IMG_20171119_124233-01"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p><p>But the story itself is actually started when I visited Germany for the first time in the end of 2017. There was nothing wrong with my life at that time, but I feel lost. I feel like I’ve been moving in circle, just like a hamster spinning in a wheel. And this one question suddenly popped out. “Am I  happy with my life?” </p><p>So then I decided that maybe I need a fresh start. As a devout planner, then I started to plan some experiments that I always wanted to do. I made a decision to replicate <a href="https://gretchenrubin.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gretchen Rubin</a>‘s experience with her <a href="/the-happiness-project-book/">Happiness Project</a> by focusing to a certain topic per month. </p><p><strong>January - Stuff</strong><br><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/48877450906/in/album-72157711281897473/" title="IMG_20180108_003130-01" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48877450906_a8e72d9a09_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1152" alt="IMG_20180108_003130-01"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p><p>I started with material stuff since I know that I’ll be moving by the end of the month. Material stuff is probably not the most important part of our life but I believe that our relationship with material stuff or how we consume them effect a lot of other areas in our life. In “Make Room for The Essentials”, I talked also a little bit about my view on minimalism.</p><p><strong>February - Food</strong><br><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/48877451181/in/album-72157711281897473/" title="IMG_20180227_121850-01" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48877451181_7e7db1ce77_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1152" alt="IMG_20180227_121850-01"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p><p>My first month in Bali, I decided to embark on a culinary marathon, while also challenge myself to be a vegetarian. There’s a saying that says “People who love to eat are always the best people” and I was intrigued to actually prove it. </p><p><strong>March - Friendship</strong></p><p>Adult friendship is hard but it’s one of the most important investment in our life. I love <a href="https://www.thecut.com/2019/06/ask-polly-my-friendships-make-me-sad.html?utm_source=fb" target="_blank" rel="noopener">this article</a> from The Cut that says that “friendships are these weirdly intimate, vital, deeply rewarding relationships that most people don’t treat with nearly enough care.” In this section, I talked about how I learned to get to know more people by initiate more <a href="/obrolan-receh/">small talks</a> and how to also nourish our relationship with our existing friends.</p><p><strong>April - Family</strong><br><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/48876919128/in/album-72157711281897473/" title="IMG_20180413_100542_01_01-02" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48876919128_96d8ccb152_k.jpg" width="1468" height="1958" alt="IMG_20180413_100542_01_01-02"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p><p>I talked about my view on family relationship. Especially on how to navigate differences by going back to our roots. And “Letting Go of Comparison” is actually my most favorite part of the book that I would definitely recommend if you have any siblings. </p><p><strong>May - Health</strong><br><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/48877649307/in/album-72157711281897473/" title="IMG_20180528_135007-01" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48877649307_281c506985_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1152" alt="IMG_20180528_135007-01"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p><p>Although it was Ramadhan when I stayed in Ubud, it doesn’t hinder me from pursuing my dream to learn yoga there. For a whole month living there, I also try to rely on my own strength to get around (that basically means walking or biking). I also talked about the easy part of healthy living that most people forget. </p><p><strong>June - Travel</strong><br><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/48877648477/in/album-72157711281897473/" title="IMG_20180610_091848-01" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48877648477_f1dc646ca6_k.jpg" width="1536" height="2048" alt="IMG_20180610_091848-01"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p><p>I knew I always wanted to go to Seattle and I made it on June 2018. I talked also about getting 70K miles and upgraded my loyalty program (including how I exhaust myself from all those trips). </p><p><strong>July - Career</strong><br><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/48877451141/in/album-72157711281897473/" title="IMG_20180709_115507-01" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48877451141_56a16fe3a8_k.jpg" width="1537" height="2048" alt="IMG_20180709_115507-01"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p><p>I’ve been postponing this topic but finally managed to talk about it on July. In this section, I cover about failure, my view on passion, and also my experience of working remotely. </p><p><strong>August - Spiritual</strong><br><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/48877648717/in/album-72157711281897473/" title="IMG_20180615_100031-01" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48877648717_6cc4a76983_k.jpg" width="1536" height="2048" alt="IMG_20180615_100031-01"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p><p>One of the most daunting section for me. Especially because I’m not really open about my view on religion. But I managed to talked about my experience of celebrating eid in the US and also my view on being a minority. </p><p><strong>September - Romance</strong><br><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/48877649502/in/album-72157711281897473/" title="IMG_20180916_200837-01" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48877649502_177fc3c108_k.jpg" width="1536" height="2048" alt="IMG_20180916_200837-01"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p><p>Another daunting section for me. I reminisce about my old childhood and how it actually shaped my view on love. I even go for an extra mile and watched lots of romance movies and read lots of books to be able to actually write for this section. In the “The Opposite of Loneliness” I also talked about how I perceive this feeling.</p><p><strong>October - Finance</strong><br><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/48876918593/in/album-72157711281897473/" title="IMG_20180909_150847-01" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48876918593_b060e756ab_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1152" alt="IMG_20180909_150847-01"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p><p>I talked about how I keep a record of my spending for the whole year and how I decided to buy a house. But not only about spending. I also talked about how we can do sharing in a better way. </p><p><strong>November - Fun</strong><br><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/48876919188/in/album-72157711281897473/" title="IMG_20181108_113410-01" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48876919188_d8bdf48265_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1152" alt="IMG_20181108_113410-01"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p><p>As much as it sounds contradictive to the topic, on “Chasing Real Conversation”, I talked about how I went on social media detox for a month. I also talked about my new hobby that just started in these recent years, which is visiting art museums. Last but not least, of course, I also talked about my hobby for reading and playing music. </p><p><strong>December - Evaluation</strong></p><p>The last month was dedicated for evaluation or assessment. In “Data-Driven Lifestyle”, I talked about how I learned to use data to base our life decision. I also reflect about what I’ve been through for the past year and what did I learned from all these experiments. </p><hr><p>The story that I have in this book is probably not new for a lot of millennials out there. It’s basically everything you will ever hear from a 20 something girl that has been living a good life until she realized that there’s probably something wrong in her that she couldn’t understand. </p><p>I would like to close this post by quoting a book that I read from Indonesian author that I recently discovered, Lala Bohang. </p><blockquote><p>I create to have some sense of control, to create a universe where I can comfortably live in. If some people feel the same resonance and want to live in the same universe I’ll welcome them with open arms, if no one cares I’ll continue anyway. Because the purpose is not to speak to other people from the beginning. The work exists simply to save me. - The Book of Invisible Questions. </p></blockquote><p>PS!</p><p>Please go <strong><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/B3azi59g0GO/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here</a></strong> if you’d like to order the book. </p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pasted-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;upload successful&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing has always been part of me. I always enjoy the whole process of c
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>For now</title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/for-now/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/for-now/</id>
    <published>2019-10-05T14:03:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-10-06T03:03:26.671Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/48850356896/in/album-72157709043860993/" title="Whistler" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48850356896_0e3dc7f2d7_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1152" alt="Whistler"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p><blockquote><p>So maybe this is what it takes to realize<br>I am grateful just that I have been alive</p></blockquote><p>I’ve been listening to Japanese-American singer, Kina Grannis’ <a href="https://open.spotify.com/track/0c99BUd87HQfzgUUQqRyds?si=FmaJXTGrRPy7V2q6LurLAQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">For Now</a> lately. She actually wrote the song when she was detained in Jakarta for 100 days in 2016. I like this song personally because it reminded me to be grateful for a simple thing like existence.</p><p>Because really, what do we look for in life? I don’t know any answer but happiness. And lately, the majority contributor of my happiness is the existence of people that I dearly love. And this is probably not the case before. I was a self-centered person and I always put myself as the top priority. And I think I mastered the art of treating myself well. However, lately, it doesn’t seem to be fulfilling anymore.</p><p>I think I cracked that breakeven point of my own happiness. This is my own theory. But I imagine that it’s a limit that tells us that we’re enough and we don’t need more so we might better serve the others. </p><p>But the most difficult part of that process is actually figuring out how to navigate different values between us and the people we love. Because when love involved, it’s difficult not to talk about sacrifices. And that is super difficult because we don’t want to hurt either part. And so, to minimize the bias, we have to really strip off our ego and try to see things from a different perspective. And empathizing is so easy to say but difficult in practice.</p><p>But again. It’s a process so I’m not expecting it to be easy anyway. I don’t want to enforce my value to someone else since it doesn’t seem to be fair. The best we can do in this situation is perhaps try to comprehend the values of the other side and making sense of the situation. Love is not easy, but I guess the love itself is enough for now.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/48850356896/in/album-72157709043860993/&quot; title=&quot;Whistler&quot; t
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Jar of thoughts" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/categories/Jar-of-thoughts/"/>
    
    
      <category term="English" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/tags/English/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Kembali ke Rumah</title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/kembali/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/kembali/</id>
    <published>2019-09-15T07:35:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-09-15T13:56:10.112Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sejujurnya beberapa akhir pekan terakhir ini saya merasa kewalahan. Mungkin karena terlalu semangat menyiapkan beberapa proyek yang harus dikerjakan secara paralel. Di satu sisi saya senang mengerjakan itu semua, namun di sisi lain rasa penat mulai merambat dan membuat saya jadi malah menghindar dari mengerjakannya. Tapi rasanya ini wajar saja, toh hidup bukan melulu tentang produktivitas.</p><p>Akhirnya, akhir pekan ini sesudah mengatur jadwal dan membuat perencanaan untuk bulan depan, saya memutuskan untuk kembali ke <a href="/a-call-from-home/">rumah virtual</a> saya. Saya sadar sudah lama tidak menulis bebas, menumpahkan keresahan, dan mencari kejelasan melalui kata-kata seperti dulu kala. Lagi-lagi, manusia memang begini. Sudah diberi berbagai kemudahan, tapi yang dipikirkan malah yang di luar jangkauannya.</p><p>Padahal jika dipikir-pikir, Tuhan sudah baik sekali pada saya selama ini. Jika tahun lalu adalah tahunnya berbagai eksperimen, maka tahun ini adalah tahun dimana saya kerap diingatkan untuk terus <a href="/gratitude/">bersyukur</a>. Jika malaikat tahu, mereka pasti akan tertawa karena kepenatan ini barang kali tidak ada apa-apanya dengan masalah yang mungkin sedang dialami teman-teman lain. Rasanya tidak pantas jika saya terlalu lama merundungkan situasi seperti ini. </p><p>Bukti lain dari Tuhan yang berbaik hati, tahun depan band favorit saya akan tur album barunya termasuk ke Asia! Ah, ini membuat saya senang dan bersemangat sekali untuk menyambut pergantian tahun. </p><p>Lagipula, Papah juga akan pulang minggu depan. Sepertinya saya memang harus kembali mengerjakan pekerjaan yang saya tunda itu agar pekan depan bisa meluangkan waktu sepenuhnya untuk keluarga. Aah, pasti senang bisa berkumpul kembali. </p><p>Tegal, 15 September 2019<br>Ditemani musik dari <a href="https://youtu.be/HncIxRDzw0c" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ardhito Pramono</a></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;Sejujurnya beberapa akhir pekan terakhir ini saya merasa kewalahan. Mungkin karena terlalu semangat menyiapkan beberapa proyek yang harus
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Jar of thoughts" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/categories/Jar-of-thoughts/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Bahasa Indonesia" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/tags/Bahasa-Indonesia/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>[music] Collide - Howie Day</title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/collide/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/collide/</id>
    <published>2019-07-11T05:31:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-07-11T06:04:52.362Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="container"><br>  <iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/8dYcM5JqBAw" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen class="video"></iframe><br></div><p>It’s such a good day to sing so I grab my guitalele and record this one. Collide is such a nostalgic song. If you haven’t heard the original version, you should <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ca9ub9rpNK4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">check this out</a>!</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/8dYcM5JqBAw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Music" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/categories/Music/"/>
    
    
      <category term="English" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/tags/English/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>[review] Educated</title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/educated/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/educated/</id>
    <published>2019-07-03T06:40:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-07-03T08:26:31.065Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/48186174871/in/album-72157692608448671/" title="2019-07-03_01-38-51" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48186174871_8ee674e750_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="2019-07-03_01-38-51"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p><p>Educated sukses menjadi salah satu memoar terbaik yang saya baca selama ini. Meskipun kisah yang Tara ceritakan bukan termasuk kisah <em>mainstream</em>, namun pesan yang dibawa oleh buku ini termasuk <em>universal</em>. Saya suka sekali komentar dari Vogue yang mengatakan: </p><blockquote><p>“Beautiful and propulsive… Despite the singularity of [Westover’s] childhood, the questions her book poses are universal: How much of ourselves should we give to those we love? And how much must we betray them to grow up?”</p></blockquote><p>Educated menceritakan kisah Tara Westover yang tumbuh besar di keluarga <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Survivalism" target="_blank" rel="noopener">survivalist</a> di Idaho. Ketika salah satu kakaknya mulai melakukan kekerasan, Tara hanya bisa memendam lukanya karena merasa tidak ada yang berada di pihaknya. Ketika akhirnya ia berhasil memasuki bangku kuliah (padahal selama 17 tahun Tara tidak pernah mengenyam bangku sekolah), pikirannya pun mulai  berkembang dan dia mulai menemukan keberanian untuk menghadapi ketidakadilan yang dia alami dari keluarganya sendiri. </p><blockquote><p>“My life was narrated for me by others. Their voices were forceful, emphatic, absolute. It had never occurred to me that my voice might be as strong as theirs.”<br>― Tara Westover, Educated </p></blockquote><p>Ayah Tara adalah penganut Mormon yang fanatik sehingga dari kecil ia terbiasa mengikuti ajaran yang diajarkan ayahnya. Lama-kelamaan, Tara sadar bahwa pahamnya tidak lagi sejalan. Ia pun mulai mengambil jarak dari keluarganya sejak itu. Apalagi keluarganya bahkan menganggap bahwa Tara dikuasai setan karena Tara menolak untuk berdamai dengan kakaknya (keluarganya menganggap kakaknya sudah bertobat karena sudah dibersihkan melalui ritual Atonement of Christ, padahal di sisi lain ia masih sering mengancam Tara).</p><p>Jika kisah yang Tara tuliskan adalah sebuah novel, saya mungkin akan berpikir <em>“yeah, sure.. It’s a fiction. Ofcourse, it’s dramatic.”</em> Tapi saya pun tidak tega membayangkan bahwa kisah tersebut terjadi secara nyata. Saya merinding membayangkan apa yang terjadi pada Tara selama masa kecilnya dan bagaimana  dia bisa bertahan selama ini. Bahkan tidak hanya bertahan, dia juga berhasil memperoleh gelar Doktor di tengah drama keluarga yang membuatnya sampai mengalami <em>mental breakdown</em>.</p><p>Di tengah pendapat yang mengatakan bahwa sekolah itu tidak lebih penting daripada <em>skill</em>, kisah Tara membuktikan bahwa pengetahuan, apapun itu bentuknya, pasti punya manfaat di kehidupan kita. Kisah Tara membuktikan bahwa edukasi masihlah penting dan relevan. <em>We don’t study to get a job. We study to educate ourselves.</em></p><blockquote><p>“Everything I had worked for, all my years of study, had been to purchase for myself this one privilege: to see and experience more truths than those given to me by my father, and to use those truths to construct my own mind. I had come to believe that the ability to evaluate many ideas, many histories, many points of view, was at the heart of what it means to self-create. If I yielded now, I would lose more than an argument. I would lose custody of my own mind. This was the price I was being asked to pay, I understood that now. What my father wanted to cast from me wasn’t a demon: it was me.”<br>― Tara Westover, Educated </p></blockquote><p>Saya sangat terharu ketika di salah satu bab, Professor Steinberg (dosen pengawas Tara ketika ia mendapat Gates Cambridge Scholarship) mengatakan bahwa Essay yang Tara buat adalah salah satu essay terbaik yang ia baca selama 30 tahun mengajar di Cambridge. Saya bersyukur Tara mendapat dukungan dari banyak orang disaat keluarganya sendiri menganggapnya dikuasai iblis Lucifer.</p><p>Bagi saya ada 2 pesan penting dari dari buku ini. Pertama, adalah bahwa kita tidak perlu menyerahkan diri pada orang yang kita sayangi. Saya yakin Tara sangat mencintai kedua orang tuanya. Namun dengan situasi yang ia hadapi, menjauh memang jadi pilihan yang terbaik. Tara menjadi contoh, bahwa kita memiliki pilihan untuk keluar dari situasi terburuk dengan keberanian meskipun ia harus membayar mahal atas keputusannya.</p><blockquote><p>“You can love someone and still choose to say goodbye to them,” she says now. “You can miss a person every day, and still be glad that they are no longer in your life.”<br>― Tara Westover, Educated </p></blockquote><p>Dan yang kedua, adalah bahwa pendidikan memang sangat berpengaruh dalam membentuk seseorang. Pendidikan membuat kita bisa merasionalkan nilai-nilai yang kita dapat dari pihak luar, membuat kita bisa berpikir dengan lebih baik, dan membuat kita memahami apa yang dahulu bahkan tidak terlihat karena kita tidak punya pengetahuan tentangnya.</p><blockquote><p>“An education is not so much about making a living as making a person.”<br>― Tara Westover, Educated</p></blockquote><p>Keberanian Tara dalam menjalani kehidupannya, mengingatkan saya akan satu kutipan yang saya sudah lupa dari mana asalnya.</p><blockquote><p>If you don’t like where you are, move. You are not a tree.</p></blockquote>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/48186174871/in/album-72157692608448671/&quot; title=&quot;2019-07-03_
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Review" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/categories/Review/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Bahasa Indonesia" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/tags/Bahasa-Indonesia/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>One can&#39;t have too much happiness</title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/too-much-happiness/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/too-much-happiness/</id>
    <published>2019-06-12T04:25:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-06-20T13:06:06.025Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/48047414341/in/dateposted-public/" title="2019-06-12_11-38-43" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48047414341_87b7c94754_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="2019-06-12_11-38-43"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p><p>We were gathered on a long table in a satay restaurant. Soup and goat satay was served along with refreshing-looking orange juice and ice tea. There were a couple more minutes left before the break fasting time and we were excited about it.</p><p>Soon after, I joined my dad who took my sister’s son outside to avoid the satay’s smoke. As the break fasting time approaching, we went inside and join the others back on the long table. </p><p>During the meal, as I was loading more satay into my mouth, I came to think about one phrase. “One can’t have too much happiness.” I see I have eaten 3 pieces of satay. There are more satays on the table but I don’t think that I want more because “one can’t have too much happiness.”</p><p>Isn’t it a strange thought? I’m eating one of my favorite food with my beloved family, why wouldn’t I want more? “One can’t have too much happiness.” </p><p>But can’t we? Of course, we can. I do think that we can do whatever makes us happy, as long as we stay civil. I think this phrase is just my coping mechanism because although one can (and should) be happy, we should also remember that there will be times when we feel the complete opposite and that’s fine too. Life is a wheel, so the rotation is inevitable. </p><p>On top of that, I do the same thing when I feel negative emotion. I always think that we should have a deadline to absorb our fear, grief or anger. Having a deadline means that we accept the emotion but also capable of controlling it.</p><p>As I was chewing my last piece of satay, I savored the texture, the tenderness, and the spice that added more richness to the flavor. And as I was looking at my mom, dad, sisters, brother, and my nephew, it almost like I can feel my blood rushes through the vein. The satisfaction is almost indescribable. It’s one of the best feelings ever!  Alhamdulillah..</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/48047414341/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;2019-06-12_11-38-
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Jar of thoughts" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/categories/Jar-of-thoughts/"/>
    
    
      <category term="English" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/tags/English/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>[review] Filosofi Teras</title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/filosofi-teras/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/filosofi-teras/</id>
    <published>2019-06-06T15:17:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-06-06T15:43:47.729Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/48013704806/in/dateposted-public/" title="2019-06-06_10-19-42" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48013704806_64dbe27b6c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="2019-06-06_10-19-42"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p><blockquote><p>Stoisisme adalah filosofi yang sangat pragmatis dengan orientasi manajemen emosi melalui kendali nalar, presepsi, dan pertimbangan. - Henry Manampiring</p></blockquote><p>Rasanya jarang sekali saya membuat resensi buku karya penulis lokal. Masalahnya, saya lebih sering baca buku non-fiksi, sedangkan industri perbukuan lokal menurut saya masih didominasi buku fiksi. Kalaupun ada yang non-fiksi, kebanyakan genrenya humor atau buku motivasi yang judulnya terkesan <em>hard-selling</em>. Jarang banget nemu yang rasanya klop sama selera saya.</p><p>Nah, kali ini adalah sebuah pengecualian yang menggembirakan. Buku Filosofi Teras karya om Henry Manampiring (aka om Piring) ini menurut saya memberi angin segar di dunia literasi lokal karena <em>genre</em> yang begini nih jarang banget ditemuin. </p><p>Meskipun jauh sebelum membaca buku ini saya udah <em>follow</em> om Piring di <a href="https://twitter.com/newsplatter" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Twitter</a>, buku ini adalah karya pertama beliau yang saya baca. <em>And I can safely say that he’s an awesome author, indeed!</em> Saya pengen bahas om Piringnya dulu nih, karena saya pikir dia termasuk penulis langka di industri literasi lokal.</p><p>Kalau kebanyakan pengarang lokal mulainya dari <em>genre</em> fiksi, atau humor, nah Om Piring ini dari awal  memang konsisten untuk membuat karya non-fiksi. Itulah yang menurut saya patut diapresiasi, karena industri buku lokal memang sangat butuh variasi <em>genre</em>. Melihat portofolio karya beliau di laman <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/author/list/6581630.Henry_Manampiring" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Goodreas-nya</a>, menurut saya buku Filosofi Teras ini, selain membuktikan kedewasaan karya si penulis, juga semakin memperkokoh posisi beliau sebagai penulis non-fiksi yang kawakan di Indonesia. </p><p>Membahas Filosofi Teras atau Stoisisme sendiri, konsep ini memang menarik bagi saya secara pribadi. Sebelum membaca buku ini pun saya sudah beberapa kali mendengar tentang filosofi ini. Mungkin itulah mengapa, bagian awal buku ini terasa agak membosankan bagi saya, karena saya sudah berkali-kali mendengar konsep dikotomi kendali sebelumnya.</p><p>Dikotomi kendali sendiri mengajarkan bahwa dalam hidup ini, ada hal-hal yang di bawah kendali kita dan ada yang tidak. Karena itulah, konsep ini menekankan supaya kita fokus ke hal-hal yang bisa kita kendalikan, dan tak perlu mengkhawatirkan hal-hal yang diluar kendali kita.</p><p>Sebelum membahas dikotomi kendali, buku ini dibuka dengan pembahasan survey khawatir nasional yang penulis adakan secara daring. Dalam survey tersebut, terkuak bahwa banyak sekali macam-macam kekhawatiran yang dirasakan oleh para peserta survey tersebut seperti kekhawatiran tentang studinya, tentang <em>relationship</em> (bagi yang memiliki hubungan) dan tentang jodoh (bagi yang lajang), tentang finansial, tentang pekerjaan, sampai orang tua yang mengkhawatirkan tentang masa depan anaknya.</p><p>Kenapa membahas tentang kekhawatiran? Karena hal ini sangat erat kaitannya dengan dikotomi kendali. Umumnya, kekhawatiran muncul karena keinginan kita untuk mengontrol hal-hal yang sebenarnya di luar kendali kita. Padahal, seharusnya kita fokus pada apa yang bisa kita kendalikan. Dalam buku ini dijelaskan lebih detil, contoh-contoh penerapan dikotomi kendali yang berkaitan dengan kehidupan sehari-hari. </p><blockquote><p>“It is not the man who has too little, but the man who craves more, that is poor.” - Seneca (Letters)</p></blockquote><p>Dalam bab Mengendalikan Interpretasi dan Presepsi, penulis memaparkan konsep STAR yang merupakan kepanjangan dari Stop,Think and Assess, dan Respond. STAR ini adalah langkah-langkah yang bisa kita gunakan untuk mengendalikan emosi negatif. Bahwa ketika merasakan emosi tersebut, kita perlu secara sadar menghentikan (stop) emosi tersebut terlebih dahulu, sebelum berpikir (think) dan menilai (assess) kejadian tersebut secara rasional, lalu diakhiri dengan aksi (respond) yang merupakan hasil dari pemikiran yang didasarkan pada nalar.</p><p>Buku ini baru benar-benar menarik bagi saya ketika memasuki bab pertengahan yang membahas banyak konsep Stoisisme seperti Premeditatio Malorum (atau yang penulis sebut sebagai Imunisasi  Mental), Amor Fati (mencintai nasib), dan Practice Poverty (latihan menderita). Premeditatio Malorum adalah teknik untuk memperkuat mental dengan membayangkan semua kejadian buruk yang mungkin terjadi di hidup kita di hari ini dan ke depannya. Sedangkan Amor Fati mengajarkan kita untuk tidak hanya menerima kejadian yang memang diluar kendali kita, namun juga untuk mencintai takdir tersebut. Yang terakhir, practice poverty, menurut saya cocok menjadi kelanjutan dari premeditatio malorum. Jika pada premeditatio malorum, kita diajak untuk membayangkan kemungkinan tersebut, practice poverty adalah memaksa kemungkinan buruk itu dalam kehidupan kita agar kita tahu rasanya berada dalam posisi kesusahan. Hal ini bisa dilakukan dengan cara berpuasa (melatih kelaparan), atau melakukan digital detox (latihan untuk hidup tanpa internet), dll. </p><blockquote><p>“Kamu sungguh sial  jika kamu tidak pernah tertimpa musibah. Karena artinya kamu menjalani hidup tanpa pernah menghadapi ‘lawan’. Tidak ada yang tahu kemampuanmu seseungguhnya - bahkan dirimu sendiri tidak” - Senece (On Providence)</p></blockquote><p>Ada bagian yang bagi saya lumayan <em>mind-blowing</em> di bagian tentang kekhawatiran orang tua. Di situ penulis sempat membahas tentang pemikiran bahwa “anak harus berbakti pada orang tua karena pengorbanan orang tua.” Padahal, membimbing dan berkorban untuk anak adalah hal yang selaras dengan alam karena itu memang kewajiban orang tua, jadi orang tua pun tidak perlu mengungkit-ungkit hal tersebut sebagai investasi.</p><p>Boom! Rasanya sangat mak jleb. Meskipun bab tersebut lebih diperuntukan untuk para orang tua, saya sendiri sebagai anak sering kali merasa <em>in-debt</em> pada kedua orang tua sehingga bab ini terasa sangat mengena. Menurut saya, sebagai anak, kita pun perlu berpikir bahwa berbakti kepada orang tua merupakan hal yang selaras dengan alam. Jadi, kita tak perlu memikirkan hal tersebut sebagai balas budi, melainkan sebagai hal yang memang patut kita lakukan sebagai anak. </p><blockquote><p>Orang-orang yang sangat menginginkan dikenang sesudah mati lupa bahwa mereka yang akan mengenangnya pun akan mati juga. Dan begitu juga orang-orang sesudahnya lagi. Sampai kenangan tentang kita, diteruskan dari satu orang ke yang lain bagaikan nyala lilin, akhirnya meredup dan padam. - Marcus Aurelius (Meditations)</p></blockquote><p>Semakin dibaca, saya pun merasa bahwa konsep stoisisme ini memang sangat sejalan dengan kepribadian saya. Bahkan, di antaranya sudah saya praktikan. Bab tujuh, yang membahas tentang orang-orang menyebalkan, mengingatkan saya pada sebuah <a href="/nurani/">tulisan lama</a>, tentang mereka yang mengabaikan hati nuraninya. Pada bab terakhir, tentang ritual untuk mempraktikan stoisisme di malam hari, bahkan menggunakan pertanyaan yang kurang lebih sama dengan pertanyaan yang saya gunakan untuk menulis <a href="https://twitter.com/kelimuttu/status/1124721856911556608" target="_blank" rel="noopener">jurnal harian</a>. </p><blockquote><p>Yang bukan saudaramu dalam  iman, adalah saudaramu dalam kemanusiaan. - Sayyidina Ali bin Abi Thalib.</p></blockquote><p>Di awal, Om Piring memang sempat bilang kalau bukunya ini diperuntukkan untuk memicu minat pembaca untuk mempelajari filosofi ini lebih dalam. Saya rasa, tujuan tersebut sangat berhasil. Karena sekarang, saya jadi penasaran banget pengen baca Meditations. </p><p><em>In a way</em>, bisa dibilang stoisisme ini mengajarkan tentang “how not to be an <em>a**hole</em>.” Dan saya rasa, ini yang membuat buku ini terasa makin penting untuk dibaca lebih banyak orang.</p><p>NB:<br><em>Thanks</em> untuk <a href="http://twitter.com/dikyarga/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Diky</a> yang merelakan bukunya untuk dibaca duluan padahal yang punya pun belum baca sampai selesai. </p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/106119858@N08/48013704806/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;2019-06-06_10-19-
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Review" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/categories/Review/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Bahasa Indonesia" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/tags/Bahasa-Indonesia/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Zavi</title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/zavi/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/zavi/</id>
    <published>2019-06-03T13:12:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-06-03T13:50:02.516Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/pasted-1.png" alt="upload successful"></p><p>Sulit rasanya mengingat bagaimana<br>aku bisa  jatuh hati padamu pertama kali<br>Padahal waktu itu,<br>tubuhmu terlihat mungil, lemah, dan tak berdaya<br>Tapi rasanya begitulah cinta terjadi<br>Ia datang begitu saja tanpa direncana</p><p>Bahkan, hanya dengan bertemu denganmu saja aku bisa sekejap lupa<br>jika hidup terkadang bisa terasa sangat sulit<br>Memang luar biasa<br>Rasanya aspirin pun tak semanjur itu untuk mengobati kesakitanku</p><p>Zavi..<br>Kelak ketika kamu besar nanti, aku harap kamu ingat selalu<br>Bisingnya dunia tak akan berpengaruh<br>jika kamu tak mengizinkan mereka untuk merusak harimu</p><p>Dunia mungkin kacau dan rumit<br>Namun kau tak perlu menyimpan kebencian pada pengacau itu<br>Barangkali, mereka hanya hilang arah</p><p>Satu lagi pesan terakhirku.<br>Bisakah kamu terus tersenyum seperti itu?<br>Dengan itu, rasanya hati tak pernah gagal untuk luluh seketika.</p><p>With love,<br>Aunty</p><hr><p>Kalo dulu pernah bikin puisi untuk <a href="/fiora/">Fiora</a>, dan <a href="/tiny-angel/">Kahfi</a>, kali ini tulisannya khusus dipersembahkan untuk ponakan tersayang, Zavian, yang lagi belajar ngoceh. Sehat selalu ya, Zavi. Aunty sayang Zavi! ❤️</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pasted-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;upload successful&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sulit rasanya mengingat bagaimana&lt;br&gt;aku bisa  jatuh hati padamu pertama 
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Poetry" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/categories/Poetry/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Bahasa Indonesia" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/tags/Bahasa-Indonesia/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Gratitude</title>
    <link href="http://kelimuttu.co/gratitude/"/>
    <id>http://kelimuttu.co/gratitude/</id>
    <published>2019-05-26T04:36:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-05-02T15:44:33.284Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1429280064633-adb9d2bea577?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;q=85&amp;fm=jpg&amp;crop=entropy&amp;cs=srgb&amp;dl=zack-minor-15104-unsplash.jpg" alt=""></p><p><em>If you’re given a time machine to fix your life, can you think of one moment that you would like to go back and get it fixed?</em></p><p>I was mulling over that question for the past week, but I couldn’t find any answers. Even more, lately I was feeling that my life seems so easy compared to the others. And as cocky as it sounds, some of my friends even confirmed that.</p><p>When I hear or see other people’ life issue, most of the time, I can’t help but think how small my own problem is, in comparison to theirs. And the strange thing is that that makes me feel like I was falling behind in life.</p><blockquote><p>Isn’t life supposed to be difficult and complicated? Am I missing something? </p></blockquote><p>Having said that, of course, it doesn’t mean that I don’t have any problem at all. It’s the scope of the problem that terrifies me. Somehow I’m afraid if I can’t handle the situation once I stumbled upon a major life issue in the future because I got used to an easy life.</p><p>When I thought about it, I think there are 2 possibilities that might have caused it. First, maybe I look down on my own problem and dramatized others’. Second, someone implies to me that maybe it’s a sign that I handle issues in my life well enough that it didn’t bug me much. I would love to believe the latter, of course. However, it seems arrogant just to think that way, and I honestly have no confidence to believe it. </p><p>But today, I realize something on a cab that took me to the station. I was thinking, regardless of the precedent, I should’ve earned it. It’s such a shame that I feel guilty to have a good life. Why would I do that? I should’ve focused more on the bright side. I should’ve thankful for having a great family, good friends, and a job that I love. </p><p>And of course, I’m not saying that I have the best life in the world. But I realized, that this life alone is a privilege that not everyone has and I should’ve made the best use of it. I should’ve cherished my loved ones more, and doing work that can benefit the others.</p><p>And I think I’ve been doing it without I realized. The community that I served, my writing, my podcast project, are my attempts to spill the water. Of course, there are many more that I could have done to extend my gratitude. But I’ll leave the floor to you all. Beyond the obvious one like donating, what do you usually do to extend your gratitude? Care to share an idea?</p><p>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@zackography" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Zack Minor</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Unsplash</a></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1429280064633-adb9d2bea577?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;q=85&amp;amp;fm=jpg&amp;amp;crop=entropy&amp;amp;cs=srgb&amp;am
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Jar of thoughts" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/categories/Jar-of-thoughts/"/>
    
    
      <category term="English" scheme="http://kelimuttu.co/tags/English/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
